<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="papd.8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>papd</refentrytitle>

    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>

    <refmiscinfo class="date">24 May 2024</refmiscinfo>

    <refmiscinfo class="source">Netatalk</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">Netatalk AFP Fileserver Manual</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="version">@netatalk_version@</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>papd</refname>

    <refpurpose>AppleTalk print server daemon</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>papd<indexterm>
          <primary>papd</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>UAM</primary>

          <secondary>User Authentication Module</secondary>
        </indexterm></command>

      <arg>-d</arg>

      <arg>-f configfile</arg>

      <arg>-p printcap</arg>

      <arg>-P pidfile</arg>

      <arg>-v</arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para><command>papd</command> is the AppleTalk printer daemon. This daemon
    accepts print jobs from AppleTalk clients (typically Macintosh computers)
    using the Printer Access Protocol (PAP). When used with System V printing
    systems, <command>papd</command> spools jobs directly into an
    <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>lpd</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry> spool directory and wakes up <command>lpd</command>
    after accepting a job from the network to have it re-examine the
    appropriate spool directory. The actual printing and spooling is handled
    entirely by <command>lpd</command>.</para>

    <para><command>papd</command> can also pipe the print job to an external
    program for processing, and this is the preferred method on systems not
    using CUPS to avoid compatibility problems with all the flavours of
    <command>lpd</command> in use.</para>

    <para>As of Netatalk 2.0, CUPS is also supported. Simply using <emphasis
    remap="B">cupsautoadd</emphasis> as the first papd.conf entry will share
    all CUPS printers automagically. It is still possible to overwrite these
    defaults by individually defining printer shares. See <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>papd.conf</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry> for details on the configuration file format.</para>

    <para><command>papd</command> is typically started at boot time from
    system init scripts or services. It first reads from its configuration
    file, <filename>papd.conf</filename>.</para>

    <para>If no configuration file is given, the hostname of the machine is
    used as the NBP name, and all options take their default value.</para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>-d</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Do not fork or disassociate from the terminal.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-f <replaceable>configfile</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Consult <replaceable>configfile</replaceable> instead of
          <filename>papd.conf</filename> for the configuration
          information.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-p <replaceable>printcap</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Consult <replaceable>printcap</replaceable> instead of
          <filename>/etc/printcap</filename> for LPD configuration
          information.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-P <replaceable>pidfile</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the file in which <command>papd</command> stores its
          process id.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-v</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Print version information and exit.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Notes</title>

    <para>PSSP<indexterm>
        <primary>PSSP</primary>

        <secondary>Print Server Security Protocol</secondary>
      </indexterm> (Print Server Security Protocol) is an authentication
    protocol<indexterm>
        <primary>authenticated printing</primary>
      </indexterm> carried out through postscript printer queries to the print
    server. Using PSSP requires LaserWriter 8.6.1 or greater on the client
    Mac. The user will be prompted to enter their username and password before
    they print. It may be necessary to re-setup the printer on each client the
    first time PSSP is enabled, so that the client can figure out that
    authentication is required to print. You can enable PSSP on a per-printer
    basis. PSSP is the recommended method of authenticating printers as it is
    more robust than CAP-style authentication, described below.</para>

    <para>CAP-style authentication<indexterm>
        <primary>CAP-style authentication</primary>

        <secondary>old-style printing authentication</secondary>
      </indexterm> gets its name from the method CAP (Columbia AppleTalk
    Package) used to authenticate its Mac clients' printing. This method
    requires that a user login to a file share before they print.
    <command>afpd</command> records the username in a temporary file named
    after the client's AppleTalk address, and it deletes the temporary file
    when the user disconnects. Therefore CAP style authentication will
    <emphasis>not</emphasis> work for clients connected to
    <command>afpd</command> via TCP/IP. <command>papd</command> gets the
    username from the file with the same AppleTalk address as the machine
    connecting to it. CAP-style authentication will work with any Mac client.
    If both CAP and PSSP are enabled for a particular printer, CAP will be
    tried first, then <command>papd</command> will fall back to PSSP.</para>

    <para>The list of UAMs to use for authentication (specified with the 'am'
    option) applies to all printers. It is not possible to define different
    authentication methods on each printer. You can specify the list of UAMS
    multiple times, but only the last setting will be used. Currently,
    <emphasis>uams_guest.so</emphasis> and <emphasis>uams_clrtxt.so</emphasis>
    are supported as printer authentication methods. The guest method requires
    a valid username, but not a password. The Cleartext UAM requires both a
    valid username and the correct password.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Print authentication is only supported on Mac OS 9 and
      earlier.</para>
    </note>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Files</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>papd.conf</filename></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Default configuration file.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>/etc/printcap</filename></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Printer capabilities database.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>.ppd</filename></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>PostScript Printer Description file. papd answers
          configuration and font queries from printing clients by consulting
          the configured PPD file. Such files are available from Adobe, Inc.,
          or from the printer's manufacturer. If no PPD file is configured,
          papd will return the default answer, possibly causing the client to
          send excessively large jobs.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Caveats</title>

    <para><command>papd</command> accepts characters with the high bit set (a
    full 8-bits) from the clients, but some PostScript printers (including
    Apple's LaserWriter family) only accept 7-bit characters on their serial
    interface by default. The same applies for some printers when they're
    accessed via TCP/IP methods (remote LPR or socket). You will need to
    configure your printer to accept a full 8 bits or take special precautions
    and convert the printjob's encoding (e.g. by using <emphasis
    remap="B">co="protocol=BCP"</emphasis> when using CUPS 1.1.19 or
    above).</para>

    <para>When printing clients run Mac OS X 10.2 or later, take care that
    PPDs do not make use of <emphasis remap="B">*cupsFilter:</emphasis>
    comments unless the appropriate filters are installed at the client's
    side, too.</para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See also</title>

    <para><citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle><citerefentry>
            <refentrytitle>lp</refentrytitle>

            <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
          </citerefentry>,lpr</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,<citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>lprm</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,<citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>printcap</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,<citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>lpc</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,<citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>lpd</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,<citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>papd.conf</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>.</para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
      <title>Author</title>

      <para>See <ulink url='https://github.com/Netatalk/netatalk/blob/main/CONTRIBUTORS'>CONTRIBUTORS</ulink></para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
