<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="upgrade">
  <chapterinfo>
    <date>06.09.2004</date>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jörg</firstname>

      <surname>Lenneis</surname>

      <contrib>initial version</contrib>
    </author>

    <pubdate>26 June, 2004</pubdate>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Upgrading from  Netatalk 1.x</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>Version 2.x of the Netatalk suite includes significant changes and
    enhancements in functionality compared to 1.x. Netatalk 2.x is
    now supported which allows UTF8-MAC encoded filenames of up to 255 bytes
    (85-255 chars) in length amongst other things. The Catalogue Node ID
    (CNID) subsystem has been reworked as well and should now be much more
    robust. For an overview of what CNIDs are and why you need them please see
    the <link linkend="CNID-backends">CNID</link> section in the
    manual.</para>

    <para>The downside of these enhancements is that upgrading to Netatalk 2.x
    is not a process that can be easily automated. Too many factors depend on
    site specific configuration and administrators have to make choices that
    suit their requirements. This document attempts to clarify the issues and
    outline the steps that need to be taken for a successful upgrade. As
    usual, the first of these steps should be to make a complete backup of all
    volumes and home directories that were in use with Netatalk before.
    Afterwards, you'll have to decide</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>what encoding to use for filenames in the future and how to
        convert existing filenames</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>what storage scheme to use for CNIDs and maybe convert an
        existing database to that scheme</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The following two sections deal with each of these areas in
    turn.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="volumes-and-filenames">
    <title>Volumes and filenames</title>

    <para>Netatalk 1.x saved filenames in the so called
    <emphasis>CAP<indexterm>
        <primary>CAP</primary>

        <secondary>Columbia AppleTalk Package</secondary>
      </indexterm></emphasis> encoding by default. Alternatively, there was
    the NLS<indexterm>
        <primary>NLS</primary>

        <secondary>Native Language Support</secondary>
      </indexterm> system, that allowed you to convert filenames to other
    codepages, like ISO-8859-1.</para>

    <para>For Netatalk 2.x the charset conversion routines had to be
    completely rewritten to support AFP 3.x. For more indepth information on
    character sets please read the <link
    linkend="charsets">Unicode/charsets</link> section in the manual.</para>

    <para>As a consequence, Netatalk 2.x now stores filenames in UTF-8 by
    default. Additionally you <emphasis role="bold">have</emphasis> to specify
    a maccodepage in afpd.conf, if your Mac clients are not using
    <emphasis>MacRoman</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>The format of the metadata files stored in the .AppleDouble folders
    has changed from AppleDouble v1 to AppleDouble v2<indexterm>
        <primary>ADv2</primary>

        <secondary>AppleDouble v2</secondary>
      </indexterm>. Netatalk 2.x is still able to use AD1 files, if
    configured. Otherwise ADv1<indexterm>
        <primary>ADv1</primary>

        <secondary>AppleDouble v1</secondary>
      </indexterm> files will silently be updated to the new ADv2 format,
    which will prevent you from using this volume with 1.x again.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>Do not share a 1.x volume with Netatalk 2.x without setting the
      proper options!</para>
    </warning>

    <para></para>

    <warning>
      <para>In case of MacChineseTraditional, MacJapanese or MacKorean,
      This method cannot be used.</para>
      <para>Before upgrading, copy all files to the client. And restore
      all files to netatalk 2.0.4 or later.</para>
    </warning>

    <para></para>

    <note>
      <para>You should consider 'upgrading' your volumes using the new
      defaults UTF-8 and AppleDouble v2, even if this is a time consuming
      process. AFP 3.x uses UTF-8 and it is impossible to fully map UTF-8 to
      any of the old volume formats.</para>
    </note>

    <para></para>

    <sect2 id="volupgrade">
      <title>How to upgrade a volume to 2.x</title>

      <para>To convert the 1.x CAP or NLS encoded volumes on the server, we
      provide the <citerefentry>
          <refentrytitle>uniconv</refentrytitle>

          <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry> utility. Please see the man page for details.</para>

      <para>Another option to perform an upgrade, is to copy all files using a
      Mac client. Either copy the volume to a Mac while you are still running
      1.6, then install 2.x and copy the data back to a fresh share, or try to
      set up the volume with the compatibility options described below and do
      a share to share copy.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="capvol">
      <title>How to use a 1.x CAP encoded volume with 2.x</title>

      <para>Using a 1.x CAP encoded volume is still possible with Netatalk
      2.x. To work properly, the following options need to be set, matching
      your 1.x setup:</para>

      <para>afpd.conf:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>maccodepage</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>AppleVolumes.default:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>volcharset</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>adouble</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>You have to make sure <option>maccodepage</option> matches your
      Apple clients codepage. For western users the default
      <emphasis>Mac_Roman</emphasis> should be fine.</para>

      <para>Set <option>volcharset</option> to
      <emphasis>ASCII</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Set <option>adouble:v1</option>, this will make sure the metadata
      files will not be changed to AppleDouble v2. If you do not set this
      option, it will not be possible to use the volume with Netatalk 1.x
      anymore.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis>:</para>

      <para><filename>afpd.conf</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting> - -transall -maccodepage:MAC_CENTRALEUROPE</programlisting>

      <para><filename>AppleVolumes.default</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting> /path/to/share "1.x Volume" adouble:v1 volcharset:ASCII</programlisting>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>How to use a 1.x NLS volume with 2.x</title>

      <para>Whether you can still use an 1.x NLS encoded volume with Netatalk
      2.x mainly depends on which NLS setting you used with 1.x.</para>

      <para>Make sure you set the correct <option>maccodepage</option> in
      <filename>afpd.conf</filename> !</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>maccode.iso8859-1</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Use the following settings in
            <filename>AppleVolumes.default</filename>:</para>

            <programlisting> /path/to/share "1.x Volume" adouble:v1 volcharset:ISO-8859-1</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>maccode.iso8859-1.adapted</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Sorry, you're out of luck. This NLS contains a non standard
            mapping and is not supported by afpd anymore. You'll have to <link
            linkend="volupgrade">convert</link> the volume to a supported
            encoding.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>maccode.437</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Using the following settings in
            <filename>AppleVolumes.default</filename> might work, but is
            untested:</para>

            <programlisting> /path/to/share "1.x Volume" adouble:v1 volcharset:CP437</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>maccode.850</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Using the following settings in
            <filename>AppleVolumes.default</filename> might work, but is
            untested:</para>

            <programlisting> /path/to/share "1.x Volume" adouble:v1 volcharset:CP850</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>maccode.koi8-r</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Using the following settings in
            <filename>AppleVolumes.default</filename> might work, but is
            untested:</para>

            <programlisting> /path/to/share "1.x Volume" adouble:v1 volcharset:KOI8-R</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para></para>

      <note>
        <para>All of the above require <ulink
        url="http://www.gnu.org/software/libiconv/">iconv</ulink> to be
        installed and to supply the volcharset codepage!</para>
      </note>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="choosecnidscheme">
    <title>Choosing a CNID<indexterm>
        <primary>CNID</primary>

        <secondary>Catalog Node ID</secondary>
      </indexterm> storage scheme</title>

    <para>Previous versions of Netatalk allocated CNIDs either on the fly or
    CNIDs were recorded in a persistent database. "On the fly methods" work by
    either generating a CNID from the device and inode number or simply by
    using a counter that is increased by one on each access to a file or
    directory from the client. The counter only lasts for the lifetime of an
    afpd daemon process and inode numbers are reused for a different file once
    the original file has been deleted. These methods therefore violate a
    fundamental assumption: A CNID once assigned must never be reused for the
    lifetime of a volume. Netatalk 2.0 supports one "On the fly scheme" called
    <emphasis remap="B">last</emphasis>. It computes CNIDs for files from
    device and inode of the file and uses a counter for directories. You
    should think twice about using it in production. Depending on your needs
    and the semantics of the underlying file system it might be OK on read
    only volumes, but even there we are not certain if OS X clients will work
    properly.</para>

    <para>That leaves the CNID schemes that use persistent storage for CNIDs.
    Netatalk 2.3 supports one: 
    <emphasis remap="B">dbd</emphasis>. It is based on the Berkeley DB
    database library as before. One difference is, though, that you are not
    restricted to using a single scheme for all of your volumes that has to be
    determined at compile time. The CNID scheme (also called a "CNID backend")
    is now a runtime option for a volume. That means that you can make the
    choice per volume based on your requirements. Here are the properties as
    well as the advantages and disadvantages of the two supported schemes:
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">last<indexterm>
              <primary>Last</primary>

              <secondary>"last" CNID backend</secondary>
            </indexterm>:</emphasis> See above. Avoid, if at all
          possible.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">dbd<indexterm>
              <primary>DBD</primary>

              <secondary>"dbd" CNID backend</secondary>
            </indexterm>:</emphasis> There is only a single daemon that
          accesses the CNID database for a given volume. Any afpd process that
          wishes to retrieve or update CNIDs for that volume needs to do it
          via the daemon. The CNID can database be (this is a compile time
          option) updated under Berkeley DB transactional protection. This
          design combined with the transactional updates makes the CNID
          database crashproof: Any of the participating afpd daemons, the
          database daemon itself or the whole machine can crash and the CNID
          database should still be in a consistent state.
          Also, have a look at the nosync
          option documented in the cnid_dbd manual page.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <para>Note that the <emphasis remap="B">dbd</emphasis> backend needs an
    auxiliary daemon, called <command>cnid_metad</command><indexterm>
        <primary>cnid_metad</primary>

        <secondary>dbd CNID database daemon</secondary>
      </indexterm>, to work. It should be started together with afpd. If the
    <emphasis remap="B">dbd</emphasis> backend is compiled into afpd (the
    default), this should happen automatically. If you cannot find it in the
    process list even though the <emphasis remap="B">dbd</emphasis> backend is
    used please check for errors in the startup scripts.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>How to upgrade if no persistent CNID storage was used</title>

      <para>That is easy. Just pick a CNID backend from above, configure it
      properly in afpd.conf and the AppleVolumes file and start up the
      necessary Netatalk processes. The databases will be automatically
      created in a subdirectory <filename>.AppleDB</filename><indexterm>
          <primary>AppleDB</primary>

          <secondary>.AppleDB CNID database store</secondary>
        </indexterm> of the volume in question.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>How to upgrade if a persistent CNID storage scheme was
      used</title>

      <para>In that case the CNID databases need to be upgraded. A script
      called cnid2_create that comes with Netatalk 2.0 does most of the work.
      The steps you have to take depend on what version of Berkeley DB is
      installed on your system. If you already use one of the supported
      versions of Berkeley DB (4.1.25 or 4.2.52) for your old Netatalk
      installation and plan to use it for Netatalk 2.0 as well just use the
      <command>db_dump</command> and <command>db_load</command> utilities that
      came with it as indicated below. Otherwise it is probably best to have
      the old and the new (to be used with Netatalk 2.0) version of Berkeley
      DB installed side by side until you have finished the upgrade. The
      reason for this is that we will dump out the old databases with the
      currently installed version of Berkeley DB in ASCII format and reload
      them with the new version. This avoids any incompatibility problems
      between Berkeley DB releases with respect to the on-disk format.</para>

      <para>For each volume to be upgraded, follow these steps <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Stop all afpd daemons accessing the volume.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Change to the database directory for that volume, most
            likely the <filename>.AppleDB</filename> subdirectory of the
            volume toplevel directory in question.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Dump the contents of <filename>cnid.db</filename> and
            <filename>didname.db</filename> using the old (installed) version
            of Berkeley DB like this:</para>

            <programlisting> db_dump -f cnid.dump cnid.db 
 db_dump -f didname.dump didname.db</programlisting>

            <para>Make sure the db_dump utility you are using is the correct
            (currently used) one. Use the full path to the db_dump executable
            if in doubt. So if this database was created with Berkeley DB 3.xx
            installed in <filename>/usr/local/db3</filename> use
            <filename>/usr/local/db3/bin/db_dump</filename> instead. This will
            create two files, <filename>cnid.dump</filename> and
            <filename>didname.dump</filename> in the current directory.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Run the cnid2_create script:</para>

            <programlisting> /path/to/netatalk/bin/cnid2_create </programlisting>

            <para>The script assumes that <filename>.AppleDB</filename> is a
            subdirectory of the volume directory to be upgraded. If that is
            not the case give the full path name of the volume as the first
            argument to <command>cnid2_create</command>. The script will
            create a file <filename>cnid2.dump</filename> in ASCII
            format.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Remove the old Berkeley DB environment and logfiles (if
            present):</para>

            <programlisting> rm __db.* log.*</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Load <filename>cnid2.dump</filename> into the new database.
            You should use the <command>db_load</command> utility of Berkeley
            DB that will be used with version 2.0 of Netatalk. So if Berkeley
            DB 4.xx lives in <filename>/usr/local/db4</filename> use</para>

            <programlisting> /usr/local/db4/bin/db_load -f cnid2.dump cnid2.db </programlisting>

            <para>This will create the new database file,
            <filename>cnid2.db</filename>. Remove the old database files
            <filename>cnid.db</filename>, <filename>didname.db</filename> and
            <filename>devino.db</filename>. The intermediate files
            <filename>cnid.dump</filename>, <filename>didname.dump</filename>
            and <filename>cnid2.dump</filename> can be removed now or at some
            later time.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>If you do not want to have two versions of Berkeley DB installed
      side by side during the upgrade, you should first dump out the old
      databases as indicated above for all volumes, upgrade Berkeley DB and
      then load them with db_load. The <command>cnid2_create</command> script
      can be run before or after the upgrade. Berkeley DB environment and
      logfiles should still be removed before running
      <command>db_load</command>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="bruteforceupgrade">
      <title>How to upgrade if a persistent CNID storage scheme was used, the
      brute force approach</title>

      <para>If you are absolutely sure what you are doing, you can also just
      clear out all database files from the <filename>.AppleDB</filename>
      directories. They will be recreated, but will <emphasis
      remap="B">not</emphasis> contain the same CNIDs as before!! That might
      lead to all sorts of problems, like aliases not working any more on
      clients. As I said, make sure you know the consequences and don't mind
      them.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="testserver">
    <title>Setting up a test server on the same machine</title>

    <para>Providing a test environment in parallel with the existing
    production installation is not difficult and, if done properly, it should
    not in any way disrupt the normal operation. However, as always, it is
    recommended to make a backup of the existing installation before
    proceeding. When compiling a newer netatalk version you should also take
    care that you do not overwrite the binaries of an older version (make use
    of the <option>--prefix=</option> configure option).</para>

    <para>There could be more than two afpd servers running on one UNIX box.
    You just have to be careful to keep them from running into each
    other:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the shares/volumes
        (<filename>AppleVolumes.default</filename>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the PID file (<command>afpd</command> <option>-P</option>
        command line option)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the port number (<option>-port</option> option in
        <filename>afpd.conf</filename>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>no use of AppleTalk (<option>-noddp</option> option in
        <filename>afpd.conf</filename>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>You should test the new Netatalk version with both a freshly created
    new share and another one that has been duplicated/converted from an
    already existing volume. This helps finding mistakes you probably made in
    the upgrade process when the first share behaves well and the latter
    not.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Setting up an empty test share</title>

      <para>First, you have to provide some space for the test share. Just
      create a directory on one of your data filesystems. However, this
      directory must not be accessible from the production afpd server. Don't
      forget to set appropriate permissions for the share. For example:</para>

      <programlisting> mkdir /macdata/testshare
 chown root.macusers /macdata/testshare
 chmod g+wrx,g+s /macdata/testshare</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Duplicating an already existing share</title>

      <para>Ensure that users cannot access the share in question and copy the
      whole contents (including all the metadata directories like
      <filename>.AppleDB</filename>) to another location.</para>

      <programlisting> cp -pr /production/testshare /macdata/</programlisting>

      <para>Then do the somewhat extensive upgrade of CNID databases and
      filename encodings outlined earlier in this chapter.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Configuring and running the test afpd</title>

      <para>Normally the test afpd cannot listen on the standard afpovertcp
      port, because that one is already bound by the production afpd. So the
      <filename>afpd.conf</filename> should look like</para>

      <programlisting> - -noddp -nouservol -port 5480 -loginmsg "WARNING: test server"</programlisting>

      <para>You also have to present the share to the Mac users by editing the
      <filename>AppleVolumes.default</filename> file. Remove the line
      containing a single "~" at the end of the file and append something
      like:</para>

      <programlisting> /macdata/testshare "Test Volume (not production)"</programlisting>

      <para>That should be the only uncommented line in the file. Do not
      forget to adjust encoding and AppleDouble setting when you're not using
      the recommended defaults UTF8 and ADv2.</para>

      <para>In case you have many users and want to restrict access to the
      test server, there is a provision for that in the
      <filename>AppleVolumes.default</filename> file. First, create a group
      named, say, <option>afpdtest</option>, and put in it all users you would
      want to enable access to the test volumes. Then, instead of the line
      above, append a line like this one:</para>

      <programlisting> /macdata/testshare "Test Volume (not production)" allow:@afpdtest</programlisting>

      <para>The test afpd server can be started now:</para>

      <programlisting> $TESTDIR/sbin/afpd -P /var/run/afpd-test.pid</programlisting>

      <para>You can also put this line in the production netatalk start
      script, in the "start" case. In the "stop" case, you should
      insert</para>

      <programlisting> [ -f /var/run/afpd-test.pid ] &amp;&amp; kill `cat /var/run/afpd-test.pid`</programlisting>

      <para>The production server has to know about the test server. Otherwise
      the Mac users would not be able to see the test server in their
      choosers. Append the following line to the production
      <filename>afpd.conf</filename> (usually in
      <filename>/etc/netatalk/afpd.conf</filename>):</para>

      <programlisting> "Test server (not production)" -proxy -uamlist "" -port 5480</programlisting>

      <para>and restart the production netatalk. Note that the port directive
      here should match the one which appears above in the test
      <filename>afpd.conf</filename>.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Note that there is a limit of 31 characters for the server's
        name. Should the name be longer, then afpd will just refuse to register
        the server.</para>
      </important>

      <para>The test server should appear in the chooser on Macs. You can also
      test that from the UNIX command line:</para>

      <programlisting> nbplkup =:AFPServer</programlisting>

      <para>or</para>

      <programlisting> netstat -an | grep 5480</programlisting>

      <para>If everything went fine spread the word about the test server
      among your more experienced Mac users and see whether things work as
      expected.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
