<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="papd.conf.5">
  <!--  $Id: papd.conf.5.xml,v 1.12 2009-07-20 08:46:34 franklahm Exp $ -->

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>papd.conf</refentrytitle>

    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>

    <refmiscinfo class="date">06 Sep 2004</refmiscinfo>

    <refmiscinfo class="source">@NETATALK_VERSION@</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>papd.conf</refname>

    <refpurpose>Configuration file used by papd(8) to determine the
    configuration of printers used by the Netatalk printing daemon<indexterm>
        <primary>papd.conf</primary>
      </indexterm></refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para><emphasis remap="B">papd.conf</emphasis> is the
    configuration file used by papd to configure the printing services offered
    by netatalk.
    <emphasis remap="B">papd</emphasis> shares the same defaults as lpd on
    many systems, but not Solaris.</para>

    <para>Any line not prefixed with <emphasis remap="B">#</emphasis> is
    interpreted. The configuration lines are composed like:</para>

    <para><emphasis remap="I">printername:[options]</emphasis></para>

    <para>On systems running a System V printing system the simplest case is
    to have either no papd.conf, or to have one that has no active lines. In
    this case, atalkd should auto-discover the local printers on the machine.
    Please note that you can split lines by using <emphasis
    remap="B">\\fR.</emphasis></para>

    <para>printername may be just a name (<emphasis remap="B">Printer
    1</emphasis>), or it may be a full name in nbp_name format (<emphasis
    remap="B">Printer 1:LaserWriter@My Zone</emphasis>).</para>

    <para>Systems using a BSD printing system should make use of a pipe to the
    printing command in question within the <emphasis remap="B">pr</emphasis>
    option (e.g. <emphasis remap="B">pr=|/usr/bin/lpr</emphasis>).</para>

    <para>When CUPS support is compiled in, then <emphasis
    remap="B">cupsautoadd </emphasis> as the first entry in papd.conf will
    automagically share all CUPS printers by papd utilizing the PPDs assigned
    in CUPS (customizable -- see below). This can be overwritten for individal
    printers by subsequently adding individual entries using the CUPS queue
    name as <emphasis remap="B">pr </emphasis> entry. Note: CUPS support is
    mutually exclusive with System V support described above.</para>

    <para>The possible options are colon delimited (<emphasis
    remap="B">:</emphasis>), and lines must be terminated with colons. The
    possible options and flags are:</para>

    <variablelist remap="TP">
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">am=(uams list)</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis remap="B">am</emphasis> option allows specific
          UAMs to be specified for a particular printer. It has no effect if
          the <emphasis remap="B">au</emphasis> flag is not present or if papd
          authentication was not built into netatalk. Note: possible values
          are <emphasis remap="B">uams_guest.so</emphasis> and <emphasis
          remap="B"> uams_clrtxt.so</emphasis> only. The first method requires
          a valid username, but no password. The second requires both a valid
          username and the correct password.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">au</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>If present, this flag enables authentication for the printer.
          Please note that papd authentication must be built into netatalk for
          this to take effect.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">co=(CUPS options)</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis remap="B">co</emphasis> option allows options to
          be passed through to CUPS (e.g. <emphasis
          remap="B">co="protocol=TBCP" </emphasis> or <emphasis
          remap="B">co="raw"</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">cupsautoadd[:type][@zone]</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>If used as the first entry in papd.conf this will share all
          CUPS printers via papd. type/zone settings as well as other
          parameters assigned to this special printer share will apply to all
          CUPS printers. Unless the <emphasis remap="B">pd</emphasis> option
          is set, the CUPS PPDs will be used. To overwrite these global
          settings for individual printers simply add them subsequently to
          papd.conf and assign different settings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">fo</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>If present, this flag enables a hack to translate line endings
          originating from pre Mac OS X LaserWriter drivers to let <emphasis
          remap="B">foomatic-rip</emphasis> recognize foomatic PPD options set
          in the printer dialog. Attention: Use with caution since this might
          corrupt binary print jobs!</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">op=(operator)</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This specifies the operator name, for lpd spooling.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">pa=(appletalk address)</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allows specification of Appletalk addresses. Usually not
          needed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">pd=(path to ppd file)</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies a particular PPD (printer description file) to
          associate with the selected printer.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">pr=(lpd/CUPS printer name or pipe
        command)</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the <emphasis remap="B">lpd</emphasis> or <emphasis
          remap="B">CUPS</emphasis> printer that this is spooled to.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>Unless CUPS support has been compiled in (which is default from
    Netatalk 2.0 on) one simply defines the lpd queue in question by setting
    the <option>pr</option> parameter to the queue name, in the following
    example "ps". If no <option>pr</option> parameter is set, the default
    printer will be used.</para>

    <example>
      <title>papd.conf System V printing system examples</title>

      <para>The first spooler is known by the AppleTalk name Mac Printer
      Spooler, and uses a PPD file located in
      <filename>/usr/share/lib/ppd</filename>. In addition, the user mcs will
      be the owner of all jobs that are spooled. The second spooler is known
      as HP Printer and all options are the default. <programlisting>Mac Printer Spooler:\
   :pr=ps:\
   :pd=/usr/share/lib/ppd/HPLJ_4M.PPD:\
   :op=mcs:

HP Printer:\
   :</programlisting></para>
    </example>

    <para>An alternative to the technique outlined above is to direct papd's
    output via a pipe into another program. Using this mechanism almost all
    printing systems can be driven.</para>

    <example>
      <title>papd.conf examples using pipes</title>

      <para>The first spooler is known as HP 8100. It pipes the print job to
      <command>/usr/bin/lpr</command> for printing. PSSP authenticated
      printing is enabled, as is CAP-style authenticated printing. Both
      methods support guest and cleartext authentication as specified by the
      '<option>am</option>' option. The PPD used is
      <filename>/etc/atalk/ppds/hp8100.ppd</filename>.
      <programlisting>HP 8100:\
   :pr=|/usr/bin/lpr -Plp:\
   :sp:\
   :ca=/tmp/print:\
   :am=uams_guest.so,uams_pam.so:\
   :pd=/etc/atalk/ppds/hp8100.ppd:
      </programlisting>
      </para>
    </example>

    <para>Starting with Netatalk 2.0 direct CUPS integration is available. In
    this case, defining only a queue name as <option>pr</option> parameter
    won't invoke the SysV lpd daemon but uses CUPS instead. Unless a specific
    PPD has been assigned using the <option>pd</option> switch, the PPD
    configured in CUPS will be used by <command>papd</command>, too.</para>

    <para>There exists one special share named "cupsautoadd". If this is
    present as the first entry then all available CUPS queues will be served
    automagically using the parameters assigned to this global share. But
    subsequent printer definitions can be used to override these global
    settings for individual spoolers.</para>

    <example>
      <title>papd.conf CUPS examples</title>

      <para>The first entry sets up automatic sharing of all CUPS printers.
      All those shares appear in the zone "1st floor" and since no additional
      settings have been made, they use the CUPS printer name as NBP name and
      use the PPD configured in CUPS. The second entry defines different
      settings for one single CUPS printer. It's NBP name is differing from
      the printer's name and the registration happens in another zone.
      <programlisting>cupsautoadd@1st floor:op=root:

Boss' LaserWriter@2nd floor:\
   :pr=laserwriter-chief:</programlisting></para>
    </example>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>

    <para><citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>papd</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>atalkd.conf</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>lpd</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>lpoptions</refentrytitle>

        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry></para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
